Now that we have seen the challenges
behind the scheduling, when we have
multiprocessor architectures hardware,
let's look at some scheduling strategies
for this kind of architectures. And
let's start with the time sharing.
So something we can do is to share one
multiprocessor detector under the time
domain. So basically all processes can run,
but they need to share overtime the resource.
We can go for something simple, yet we can have
a single system wide data structure. In this case
we can have priorities and then within each
priority level we could iterate using around
robbing and we keep your older ready threads
and whenever CPU goes idle we take the next.
Already process we have in the queue
with the August priority. So when this
CPO four goes, either we put
process a which was here.
The first with the Argus priority, then
CPU to outflows idol. We take big which
was here the current next ready process with
the August priority, and so on and so forth.
It's.
Either teams, it balances the
load automatically 'cause after
awhile all threads will be used and all.
Sorry, of course will be used in all
threads, can be assigned to any color.
There can be of course, contain contention because
you have a single infrastructure where you keep
everything but you suffer from the affinity
problem. The one I mentioned before about the
fact that course have their own caches, and if
you schedule a thread in the same corner it was
running before, then there are chances that
you will find the thread will find some stuff
in the cash that is already valid and it will
require less interaction with the main memory.
So it will perform better.
What you can do is to about two level
scheduling algorithm when you go for
a time sharing option. OK, so you could have.
These data structures, or let's say,
the collection of threads you have,
you can have one for each CPU and you assign
these threads to the CPUs at creation time.
Of course it doesn't need to be straight,
meaning that if a CPU has nothing to do is
still better to steal some threads and
or something that even if these threads
are assigned to other CPUs that just let
the CPU or wasted OK. But you still have
a, you can still achieve achieve a balance
load, but then you have also cache affinity
because you will type ability, place each
thread back to the Corey what so it was
running before and also less contention
because you have this dedicated per CPU.
Lists or sets of threads.
Something different you can do is then
instead of timesharing to go for space
sharing. So when a set of related threads OK,
so a process that is multithreaded is created.
The operating system, assuming there are of
course, enough course enough CPUs, it will
try to schedule all the threads at the same time
OK, and then it lets the Trump's that writes run.
Until they're done OK, here we don't care about
the time dimension, so if one specific thread that
belongs to a group soft red is actually
requesting some input output, we don't
release the CPU core to give it
to another thread. We just wait
for the input output to be done, and
then we keep running all the threads,
as are all the things that belong to the
same process as a single block, and they are.
Placed into the same CPU so close by, and this can
also be beneficial. As we said before,
for nonuniform memory architectures.
Then what you can do is in practice to go for a
mixture of the two, so you shall both on time and
in in space. And this is what the
gang scheduling is. So you see that.
The problem with space sharing is that they can
be inefficient 'cause we have a lot of
higher bound processes, why would you?
Waste course giving them to threads that are
just waiting instead of reallocating them to
something else, but on the other
hand, if you go for time sharing,
you can have situations like the
following. One year. Suppose you
have a seat on the A1. They're two threads.
They belong to the same process and they.
One is a producer and monitor
consumer, so they need to communicate.
You can end up scheduling that reads like this,
so it's a zero that runs than a 180 and one and
so here you could potentially waste a
lot of time because a zero it starts
running but sends a message to a one and
until A1 does not reply, a zero can not.
More forward so this entire
quantum can go basically wasted,
cause a zero is waiting for reply from a
one. Then you start running a one here.
It sends the reply back to zero and
then it does nothing to do until 80.
As you request.
And this quantum is also wasted and you
can see that you can end up in this kind
of situations if you just try to schedule
on on time. OK, So what you do is that you
try to schedule groups of related threads
at the same time, but also close by. So
trying to take into account both time and
space, OK or gang members run at once.
And all gang members start under Quantum together.
This is just an example of a possible
execution, so you have six CPUs here,
and these are the time slot. So you
see that for a certain slot you run
process a task 6 threads at the slot
2 you're on on the first three CPUs B,
and on the last three C. Then you run the hear
me and you keep running E on all the users in
the next Lotus on. So you can see that there is
time sharing, but then there is also groups of
threads that belong to the same process that
are run at the same time to maximize also.
Space sharing